# 今天年又來摘一點兄弟家的茶葉啊
We come again to pick my buddy's tea leaves this year.
# 回去做個茶葉蛋吃
Let's make a tea egg at home.
# 這茶葉很嫩的
These leaves are really young.
# 你看這個茶葉 剛剛長出個嫩葉子來哦
Look at the leaves. The young ones have just started growing.
# 這個很嫩的
These are really young.
# 只要那個
We just want the,
# 那個嫩芽 一點點就夠了
the shoots, a little bit of the shoots, not too much.
# 按 按著摘 不然它老是
I put it, put it under my arm. Otherwise, it's always,
# 晃來晃去
swinging here and there
# 這個葉不摘掉也會老掉的
The tea leaves would get old even if they're left here.
# 老的很快的
They get old really quickly.
# 你看 這個 每一片葉子下面都長了一個嫩芽
Look! Here! There's a shoot below each leaf.
# 很嫩的哦 一摘就斷
They are really young. I can pick them out without much effort.
# 這一個不要
I'm not taking this part.
# 插回去
Let me put it back
# 你看 摘了那麼多啦
Look! We have a lot here now!
# 好香啊 這個
It smells really good!
# 搓起來更香
It smells even better when it's squeezed.
# 準備回去
Let's get ready to go back.
# 你看 這邊好多
Look! Here are a lot!
# 這個很漂亮的 一茶都是 (註︰怎麼是「一茶都是」？)
It's really pretty! All over the tea...
# 要把茶葉修一下 就打(?)很多茶葉出來
A lot of leaves are growing out after cutting away some leaves.
# 這個都沒人修的
But no one does that,
# 兄弟家又一條
neither my buddy,
# 每年都是我幫他修
except me. I do it for him every year.
# 先把這個茶葉 先把它搞
Let's put the tea leaves here first, and then, well,
# 先把它烘乾來
then let's dry them over heat.
# 這溫度有點燙
The temperature is rather high.
# 它溫度又不能太燙
But in fact it shouldn't be too high.
# 再搓一下
Let' squeeze them.
# 燙啊
Hot!
# 這個條要很有耐心的
Doing this job requires a lot of patience.
# 不然做不到
Patience is essential.
# 做的很漂亮的
It's really pretty.
# 我們
I mean,
# 我們村的老人家做的很靚的 我做的就怎麼好
the elderlies in our village can make really beautiful tea leaves. But I can't make anything appealing.
# 再搓一下
Squeeze again
# 一搓就把它
They become a ball,
# 搓成一團去了
whenever I squeeze them.
# 你看 差不多好啦
Look! It's almost done.
# 有點像茶葉啦
They start to look like tea leaves now.
# 好香啊 這茶葉 真的
It smells so good! The leaves are, really...
# 這個茶葉搞好啦
So the tea leaves are ready now.
# 很漂亮的哦
It's so pretty!
# 你看 綠色的
Look! It's green,
# 深綠色的
dark green.
# 我去檢兩個雞蛋回來
Let me pick a couple of eggs.
# 這個有一個雞窩的哦 有蛋
Here's a chicken nest. Yea, eggs!
# 哇 這里有
Wa! Eggs!
# 有五個
Not one but five!
# 這裡面也有個雞窩的
There's another chicken nest inside.
# 這裡也有五個雞蛋哦
Here are five eggs too.
# 剛好煮十個 十個蛋
Ten is a good number, ten eggs.
# 這個是正宗的土雞蛋哦
These are authentic free-range eggs.
# 這是我自家養的雞
They're from my own hens.
# 你看 就這個 就它 跟它
Look! It's that one, that one, and that one.
# 兩個母雞下的
The eggs are from these two hens.
# 借你的蛋用一下
Lend me your eggs for a while!
# 哇
Wa!
# 這個
It ah,
# 應該 快熟啦
should be, almost done!
# 要它把
I need to,
# 要一個個把它敲破才行的這個
I need to crack their shells one by one, you know.
# 放點鹽下去
Put some salt.
# 這個鹽要放多一點 因為水比較多
I need a bit more salt as there's too much water.
# 放點鹽
Put some salt.
# 放點 醬油
Put some, soy sauce.
# 再放點這個茶葉
And then some, you know, you tea leaves.
# 正宗的茶葉蛋
Authentic tea eggs!
# 是不是這樣做的
Am I doing it right?
# 我也
It's,
# 第一次做
my first time.
# 先把蓋子蓋起來
Let me cover it first.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells so good!
# *華農哥別吃我 (註︰以下有*號的是B站「紅色激情」做的鬼畜，歌詞翻譯要考慮旋律)
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *給你穿女裝
Girl's costume for you.
# *華農哥別吃我
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *給你穿女裝
Girl's costume for you.
# *白色女裝好漂亮
White girl's costume so pretty.
# *免死金牌噹噹響
Amnesty medal ding dong ding
# *真漂亮 真漂亮
So pretty, so pretty
# *我要穿女裝
I want girl's costume!
# *華農哥別吃我
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *我幫你送終
I show condolence
# *華農哥別吃我
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *我幫你送終
I show condolence
# *老子還能活很久
I still have a long long life
# *今天先給你送終
Let me show condolence first
# *拔了毛 放點葱
Pluck first, spring onions
# *文火三分鐘
Low heat three minutes.
# *華農哥別吃我
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *我給你下蛋
I lay eggs for you.
# *華農哥別吃我
Sir Huanong, don't eat me!
# *我給你下蛋
I'll lay eggs for you.
# *你家公雞能下蛋?
Can your rooster lay some eggs?
# *切開肚皮看一看?
Would you open its belly?
# *你看看 你看看
Have a look! Have a look!
# *公雞沒有蛋
Rooster has no eggs!
# 看一下熟了沒有
Let me see if it's done.
# 哇 這肯定熟的
Wa! It's done, undoubtedly.
# 先來 嘗一個
Let me, try one first.
# 顏色都變了
The colour has already changed.
# 變色了
It has changed.
# 看上去都好吃
It looks really tasty.
# 變紫色了
It has turned purple.
# 好燙啊 我去泡一下水
It's hot! Let me rinse it.
# 哇塞 你看
Wa, gosh! Look!
# 看著就靚
It's so beautiful!
# 看上去就
It looks really,
# 好吃 看上去就好吃
tasty. It looks really tasty.
# 可以呦
It's not bad!
# 這個是土雞蛋來的
It's our local egg here.
# 味道完全
It taste completely,
# 不一樣
different.
# 你看 這蛋黃
Look! The egg yolk,
# 很鮮黃
the colour is so bright.
# 就是這個雞蛋 這個雞蛋小了一點
My only complaint is that the egg, the egg is a bit too small.
# 不是很大
It's not big.
# 你看這個茶葉蛋變成這樣顏色 變紫色了
Look! The colour of the tea eggs has changed, changed to purple.
# 可以吃了
We can enjoy them now.
# 放在桌子上
Let me put them on the table,
# 放到里面吃
take them inside.
# 你看 這個雞蛋有茶葉味了哦
Look! The egg now has the flavour of tea leaves,
# 淡淡的香味
a subtle fragrance.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以
Not bad!
# 好吃是吧
Isn't it tasty?
# 很好吃 真的
It's really tasty, no kidding.
# 比外面買的還好吃
It tastes even better than those sold in shops.
# 啊呀 是啊 這蠻好吃的
Aya.
Yea, it's rather tasty.
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我先把它吃完再說
Let me finish it first.
# 好燙
Very hot!